Guide to the Horticultural Society of New York Records 1811-circa 2010 (bulk, 1900-circa 2010) MS 3033
New-York Historical Society
- Series II. Library & Archives Files, 1926-circa 2010; 211478; 10.83 Linear feet
  - Subseries II.C. Librarian Files, 1970s-2008; 211521; 4.75 Linear feet
    The subseries is arranged in alphabetical order by subject matter, which follows the original order. The documents remain in their original folders. Most of the folders in the subseries were found together as a set by the processing archivist, who integrated related folders found separately into the basic set. Some subject matter can be found filed under different headings.
    - Subjects. A: General (3 of 5 folders), 1990s-2000s; 211522 (Offsite-box 54, Folder 17-19)
      Includes acknowledgements to Library of assistance rendered, Librarian activities, and annual reports of the Library.
    - Subjects. A: General (2 of 5 folders), 1990s; 211523 (Offsite-box 55, Folder 1-2)
      Includes files concerning the Hort's Archives Project, including a conservation survey of the Library's photograph collections.
    - Subjects. Benefits (7 folders), 1999-2006; 211525 (Offsite-box 55, Folder 3-9)
    - Subjects. Board (2 folders), 1990s-2008; 211528 (Offsite-box 55, Folder 10-11)
      Includes Librarian reports to the Board, some Executive Committee meeting material (1990s), and Board retreats (1995, 2008)
    - Subjects. Book Lists (2 folders), 1990s-2000s; 211527 (Offsite-box 55, Folder 12-13)
      Includes bibliographies, book recommendations, and other plant-related reference material.
    - Subjects. Book Talks (2 folders), 2000s; 211526 (Offsite-box 56, Folder 1-2)
      Includes Booked for Lunch, Booked for Dinner, and other talk programs, including one by Raymond J. Evison. The Evison material includes a set of stamps from the Bailiwick of Guernsey picturing clematis bred or developed by Evison.
    - Subjects. Budget (2 folders), 1990s-2000s; 211529 (Offsite-box 56, Folder 3-4)
    - Subjects. Collection Development Policy; Collection Size, 1990s; 211537 (Offsite-box 56, Folder 5)
    - Subjects. Community Gardens, 1999-2001; 211538 (Offsite-box 56, Folder 6)
      Includes a table "Green Thumb Group Tracking information" identifying gardens by location and name in the five New York City boroughs.
    - Subjects. C: General (2 folders), 1970s-2000s; 211535 (Offsite-box 56, Folder 7-8)
      Includes files on children's books, arrangements for a meeting of the Council on Botanical & Horticultural Libraries (1991), and a program from the Hort's Centennial Celebration Dinner Dance (16 November 1999).
    - Subjects. D: General, 1999-2003; 211576 (Offsite-box 56, Folder 9)
      Includes book donation information (see also Gifts below), most specifically those of Ruth Classen, of Thomas Powell, and of Denise Otis, disaster recovery, information about the Dyckman Farmhouse Museum (including color snapshots of the building and grounds), and information about Hort's earlier connections with the Doris Duke Foundation and gardens.
    - Subjects. Employee Handbook, 2001; 211579 (Offsite-box 56, Folder 10)
    - Subjects. Exhibits, 1990s-2000s; 211939 (Offsite-box 56, Folder 11)
    - Subjects. Flower Show Manual, 1998, 2002; 211580 (Offsite-box 56, Folder 12)
      Includes two manuals, both from the Garden Club of America's Flower Show Committee.
    - Subjects. Funding (4 folders), 1990s-2000s; 211581 (Offsite-box 56, Folder 13-16)
    - Subjects. Gardens, 1970s-1990s; 211628 (Offsite-box 57, Folder 1)
      Includes reference material including, among others, Hort's "Walking Tour of Selected Atriums, Plazas, and Vest Pocket Gardens in Midtown Manhattan" and brochures for "Gardens in New York City" (1972), "A Fifth Avenue Walking Tour," "Directory of Community Gardens in New York City" (1976), and the D'Ag (D'Agostino Grocers) map of "great picnic places, parks and undiscovered spots in Manhattan."
    - Subjects. Gifts (7 folders), 1989-2005; 211632 (Offsite-box 57, Folder 2-8)
      Includes primarily lists, correspondence and acknowledgements related to donations of books to the Library. Also includes some financial donations.
    - Subjects. G: General, 1990s; 211633 (Offsite-box 57, Folder 9)
      Includes strategic goals for the Library (1996) and related documents, images from glass slides, and reference material on the Garden Conservancy.
    - Subjects. Hand-Outs, 2000s; 211634 (Offsite-box 57, Folder 10)
      Includes topical bibliographies, reading recommendations, event announcements, and Library signage.
    - Subjects. H: General, 1990s-2000s; 211635 (Offsite-box 57, Folder 11)
      Includes records of Hort's donation of books from the Clarence and Alice Hay library to the Garden Conservancy (1996) and reference material on horticulture therapy.
    - Subjects. I: General (3 folders), 1990s-2000s; 211637 (Offsite-box 57, Folder 12-14)
      Includes records of income received by the Library for used books, photocopies, etc. (2004-06); research inquiries (2000s); an intern program outline (1990s); and lists for insurance (ca. 2000).
    - Subjects. Job Description, 1990s-2000s; 211661 (Offsite-box 57, Folder 15)
    - Subjects. Library Committee (4 of 8 folders), 1990s-2006; 211662 (Offsite-box 57, Folder 16-19)
    - Subjects. Library Committee (4 of 8 folders), 1990s-2006; 211663 (Offsite-box 58, Folder 1-4)
    - Subjects. Library General (3 folders), 1990s-2000s; 211669 (Offsite-box 58, Folder 5-7)
    - Subjects. Membership, 1998; 211744 (Offsite-box 58, Folder 8)
      Includes the 1998 member list.
    - Subjects. New Books List, 1990s; 211679 (Offsite-box 58, Folder 9)
    - Subjects. New York is Book Country (4 folders), 1991-2003; 211683 (Offsite-box 58, Folder 10-13)
    - Subjects. N: General, 1995-2007; 211684 (Offsite-box 58, Folder 14)
      Includes a New York Times article about Powis and the Library (2007), working files for the Hort newsletter, and reference material on Ninfa.
    - Subjects. On-Line Catalog Project (2 folders), 1998-2005; 211685 (Offsite-box 58, Folder 15-16)
    - Subjects. Press/Promotional, 1988-2003; 211689 (Offsite-box 59, Folder 1)
      Includes a Hort development packet of program/membership information (2003).
    - Subjects. Programs, 1995-2002; 211746 (Offsite-box 59, Folder 2)
      General Note
      Includes Apple Seed curriculum (1995); Newsday article regarding the GreenHouse program at Rikers Island (2000) and reflections of a horticultural therapist intern with the GreenHouse and GreenTeam programs (2003); program updates (1998-2002); and other material.
    - Subjects. R-T: General, 1990s-2000; 211691 (Offsite-box 59, Folder 3)
      Includes renovation work in the Library (1997) and equipment, reference information on rooftop gardens, copies of tax exemption certificate, and a photograph/slide of Webster Hall.
    - Subjects: Staff (2 folders), 1990s-2002; 211790 (Offsite-box 59, Folder 4-5)
      Includes staff lists, staff meeting notes, photographs of some staff, and other documents.
    - Subjects. Strategic Planning/Mission Statement, 1990s-2006; 211791 (Offsite-box 59, Folder 6)
    - Subjects. Usage (Library), 1992-2000; 211697 (Offsite-box 59, Folder 7)
    - Subjects. Volunteers (2 folders), 1990s-2005; 211698 (Offsite-box 59, Folder 8-9)
      Includes programs from volunteer appreciation events, photographs from the February 2000 event, applications and requests for volunteers, some correspondence from volunteers, assignments, obituaries for Volunteer Coordinator Verdalee Tombelaine (2005), and other material.
    - Subjects. W-Z, 2000, 2008-2010; 211700 (Offsite-box 59, Folder 10)
      Includes print-outs of Hort's website (2008) and book recommendations from Abbie Zabar (2000).
  - Subseries II.D. Archives Files, 1930s-circa 2010; 212199; 4.5 Linear feet
    The subseries includes files related to projects from the 1990s-early 2000s during which time archival material was compiled by the Hort and used to create ready reference resources for internal and external inquiries about the organization. The name Joan Nichols appears often in these files; Joan appears to have been the volunteer primarily responsible for implementing the archives initiative, under the direction of Librarian Katherine Powis. During processing of the collection at N-YHS in 2017, much of the original material compiled was sorted into various series (e.g., Flower Show, Print Matter, etc.). However, some material could not be readily sorted and so was kept together in this subseries. Consequently, the subseries includes a wide range of documents related to Hort's programs and administration. Most of the original material in the subseries dates from the 1980s-2000s, though there are a few earlier original pieces. Much of the subseries includes photocopies of historical documents (e.g., officer lists from annual reports of various years). The date range used in the container list refers to original documents, not the dates of photocopied material.
    Several of the folders in the subseries with original documents relate to the Hort's public education programs of the 1980s-2000s. Among these were Greenworks (later, GreenHouse), which was vocational training for inmates at Rikers Island; Green Team, which trained at-risk youth in greening projects in public spaces; GreenBranches, which installed gardens around selected branch libraries; Apple Seed, which was an environmental and science education program for the third through sixth grades; and other urban horticulture, community gardening, and related educational programs.
    The subseries also holds many files concerning administrative matters. Although much of this is photocopied material, there are several useful original documents, especially from the 1980s, including budget and financial statements, a long range plan, and the results of a member survey.
    The latter part of the subseries includes many files related to the archives project itself. These include drafts and notes related to the development of a historical timeline for the Hort, as well as general notes concerning the project and the development of the archives. These files also include preliminary partial finding aids and inventories of records created during the project.
    The subseries is roughly arranged by subject. Program-oriented files open the subseries, followed by files related to general publicity and then administration. The subseries closes with working files from the Hort's archives and historical research initiatives.
    - Pilgrimages/Tours (5 folders), 1930s-2000s; 212236 (Offsite-box 59, Folder 11-15)
    - History of Exhibits at Monthly Meetings, 1944-1945; 212237 (Offsite-box 59, Folder 16)
      Includes lists of winners of awards for horticulture exhibits at the monthly meetings and at annual shows (e.g., narcissus, gladiolus).
    - Photograph "Method of Carrying Prize Stickers", 1935 November; 212239 (Offsite-box 59, Folder 17)
    - Flower Shows (4 folders), 1980s-1990s; 212240 (Offsite-box 59, Folder 18-21)
    - Exhibitions (6 folders), 1999-2000s; 212377 (Offsite-box 60, Folder 1-6)
      Includes folders concerning Hort exhibitions (other than Flower Shows) primarily from the early 2000s. At least one folder has related articles/print matter from the 1930s.
    - Transcriptions of Taped Lectures, 1967-1968; 212421 (Offsite-box 60, Folder 7)
      Includes George Tamoulis on pot gardening outdoors, Helen Whitman on growing herbs, C. Roy Boutard on the Berkshire Garden Center, and Harry B. Kuesel on irises.
    - Horticultural Therapy Training Program (6 folders), 1975-1977, 2007; 212401 (Offsite-box 60, Folder 8-13)
    - "A Tree for New York" Program, 1968-1971; 212440 (Offsite-box 60, Folder 14)
    - "Food for Life" Program, 1983-1984; 212445 (Offsite-box 60, Folder 15)
    - "Green Team" Program, 1995-2006; 212470 (Offsite-box 60, Folder 16)
    - Community Garden Programs (3 folders), 1969-1980s; 212473 (Offsite-box 60, Folder 17-19)
      Includes Tree Corps, including photographs, and Harvest Festival.
    - Urban Gardening, 1980-1981; 212612 (Offsite-box 60, Folder 20)
      Includes a mission statement for the Neighborhood Open Space Coalition, photocopies of letters to the Parks Department concerning the proposed installation of Gates in Central Park by the artist Christo, Hort's recommendations for city plants and window boxes, and Hort's wish list for plants for its house plants exhibit at 58th Street.
    - Harlem Project Proposal, 1992; 212474 (Offsite-box 60, Folder 21)
    - West Harlem Group Assistance, Inc. Project, 1993; 212485 (Offsite-box 60, Folder 22)
      Includes documents for intergenerational programs at Mannie L. Wilson Towers, Harriet Tubman Family Living Center, and Convent Avenue Family Living Center.
    - "Greenways" Programs (2 folders), 1990s-2000s; 212478 (Offsite-box 61, Folder 1-2)
      Includes GreenWorks and GreenHouse (Rikers Island programs) and GreenBranches (library gardens).
    - "Apple Seed" and "Read & Seed" Programs, 1995-2008; 212480 (Offsite-box 61, Folder 3)
    - Awards (4 folders), 1941, 1960s-2005; 212508 (Offsite-box 61, Folder 4-7)
      Includes Certificate of Award from the New York Employing Printers Association (1941); American Association of Museums Award of distinction for Posters (1992); Association for a Better New York award for the "Gardens of the Worlds" Flower Show (1995); booklet for the New York City Art Commission's Annual Awards for Excellence in Design (1998) that included recognition of Hort's GreenBranches program; photographs of distinguished service award recipients (1960s-70s); and a description of the New York City school system's gardening program (1969-70).
    - Awards. Oversize, 1965-1971; 212509 (Offsite-box 108, Box FF-5, Folder 1)
      Includes three awards presented to Henrietta E.S. Lockwood: New York Botanical Garden's Distinguished Service Award, City Gardens Club of New York City's Citation for creating the Bryant Park Flower Show, and from the Hort for the Bryant Park Show.
    - Annual Awards Luncheon Reservation Cards, 1971-1972; 212518 (Offsite-box 61, Folder 8)
    - Press Kits (2 folders), 1980s-1990s; 212520 (Offsite-box 61, Folder 9-10)
    - Publicity. Cippings (2 folders), 1930s-2000s; 212530 (Offsite-box 61, Folder 11-12)
      Includes, among other documents, press clips of 1999 compiled by GBR Communications for Hort.
    - Publicity. Miscellaneous, 1998-1999; 212617 (Offsite-box 61, Folder 13)
      Includes consideration of a logo design.
    - Garden Magazine Survey Results, 1981; 212613 (Offsite-box 61, Folder 14)
      Includes the results of a survey of Hort members.
    - Charles Webster's "Potpourri" and Other Writings, 1969-1980s; 212616 (Offsite-box 61, Folder 15-16)
    - Garden Shop, 1980s-2000s; 212615 (Offsite-box 61, Folder 17)
      Includes advertisements and other ephemera related to the Hort store.
    - Programs. Miscellaneous, 1980s-2000s; 212555 (Offsite-box 61, Folder 18)
    - Library, 1930-1980s; 212618 (Offsite-box 61, Folder 19)
      Includes a letter to the Library about judging daffodils (1930), acquisition statistics (1956-1958), bindery costs (1949-1956), reference statistics (1981-1983), bookplates, and Library information ephemera.
    - Long Range Plans, 1960s-1990s; 212619 (Offsite-box 61, Folder 20)
      Includes, among other documents, an original of the Master Plan Committee's Long Range Plan for 1983-1992.
    - Officers (6 folders), 1980s-2000s; 212624 (Offsite-box 62, Folder 1-6)
      Includes a few original documents from the Board/Executive Director/President office of the 1970s-90s. Most documents are photocopies of historical documents identifying past officers.
    - Staff, 1947-2004; 212625 (Offsite-box 62, Folder 7)
      Includes a small number of job descriptions, organization charts, volunteer lists, and other documents. A 1947 document relates to the possibility of creating an employee pension fund.
    - Membership (3 folders), 2000s; 212627 (Offsite-box 62, Folder 8-10)
      Includes photocopies of historical documents concerning members.
    - Linnaean Fellows Dinner, 1972; 212632 (Offsite-box 62, Folder 11)
      Includes invitations, lists and related correspondence concerning the dinner, held jointly with trustees of the Pacific Tropical Botanical Garden.
    - Financial (2 folders), 1980s; 212634 (Offsite-box 62, Folder 12-13)
      Includes preliminary and final financial statements, and correspondence with accountants Davies & Davies.
    - Fundraising/Revenue (2 folders), 1965-2000s; 212635 (Offsite-box 62, Folder 14-15)
      Includes documents related to a financial legacy from John B. Turner (1965), lists of potential benefactors (1985), and various appeals and solicitations (1990s-2000s).
    - Historical Timeline Notes (4 folders), 2000s; 212640 (Offsite-box 63, Folder 1-4)
      Includes notes and photocopies related to identifying key events in Hort's history. The files include some original documents but these are generally copies of print matter or handouts likely also found elsewhere in the collection.
    - Historical Timeline Cards, 2000s; 212641 (Offsite-box 63, Cards -)
      Includes a small box of index cards and small notes recording milestone events in chronological order and other useful historical facts.
    - Archives Project Work Files (6 of 10 folders), 1990s-2000s; 212651 (Offsite-box 63, Folder 5-10)
    - Archives Project Work Files (4 of 10 folders), 1990s-2000s; 212652 (Offsite-box 65, Folder 14-17)
      Includes preliminary inventories and partial finding aids, in rough form, for the records.
- Series III. Flower Show Records, 1908-2000s; 205374; 17.67 Linear feet
  Series III. Flower Show Records, 1908-2000s is divided into the following subseries:
  Subseries III.A. Meeting Minutes & Working Files, 1915-2000s
  Subseries III.B. Print Matter and Ephemera, 1908-1996
  Subseries III.C. Photographs and Scrapbooks, 1916-1998
  This series documents the various Flower Shows organized by the HSNY from 1916-1998. These include the International Flower Show, the New York Flower Show, the Bryant Park Flower Show and the HSNY Flower Show. The records are arranged into three subseries based on format: Meeting Minutes & Working Files; Print Matter and Ephemera; and Photographs and Scrapbooks. The subseries are arranged by event.
  Meeting Minutes and Working Files primarily includes the minutes of the meetings related to the planning of the International Flower Shows and the New York Flower Shows. For the years 1942 to 1970 these records include the Board of Directors meeting minutes for International Flower Show, Inc., the corporate body created to organize and run the shows over that period. Prior to 1942, and for the New York Flower Shows, informal committees conducted the planning. These minutes provide insight into the strategic, financial, legal, and other issues surrounding the various Flower Shows.
  This subseries also includes various working files and publicity files, especially for the New York Flower Shows. The files include floor plans for some of the International Flower Shows of the 1960s, held at the New York Coliseum building; a 1969 memo from Horticultural Society of New York Executive Director Alexander Allport titled "The Future of the International Flower Show," which expressed concerns that would eventually lead to the termination of those shows; publicity packets for the New York shows; sponsor lists; logistical notes; and other items.
  Print Matter & Ephemera includes bound and loose copies of International Flower Show (IFS) official programs (1913-1970); IFS schedules (1913-1970); Horticultural Society of New York (HSNY) schedule of classes and premiums (1908-1935); HSNY programs/flower show books (1922-1965); HSNY Autumn exhibition programs (1946-1953); HSNY Narcissus & Spring show programs (1936-1958); HSNY Flower Show Schedules (1956-1973); New York Flower Show programs (1985-1996; note that there was no 1994 New York Flower Show); Rockefeller Center Flower Show program (1994); flower show promotional ephemera (1984-1996).
  Photographs and Scrapbooks includes images (i.e., photographic prints, slide, glass lantern slides, negatives, and contact prints) of the International Flower Show (1916-1969), the New York Flower Show (1936-1996, with scrapbooks for the 1988, 1992, 1993, and 1995 shows), the Bryant Park Flower Show (1969-1978, with a scrapbook honoring the achievements of Henrietta Sedgwick Lockwood, creator of the Bryant Park Flower Show), and a handful of smaller shows, like the Rockefeller Center Flower Show (1994), Boston Flower Show (1995), and Philadelphia Flower Show (1981, 1998).
  - Subseries III.A. Meeting Minutes & Working Files, 1915-2000s; 205706; 6.75 Linear feet
    The subseries is arranged by flower show, which also advances in rough chronological order. The subseries opens with the records related to the International Flower Show (1915-1970), a few miscellaneous flower shows of the 1970s, and the records related to the New York Flower Shows of the 1980s and 1990s.
    The subseries primarily includes the minutes of the meetings related to the planning of the International Flower Shows for the years 1916 to 1970 (though there were no shows in some years) and for the New York Flower Shows of the 1980s and 1990s. For the years 1942 to 1970 these records include the Board of Directors meeting minutes for International Flower Show, Inc., the corporate body created to organize and run the shows over that period. Prior to 1942, and for the New York Flower Shows, informal committees conducted the planning. These minutes provide insight into the strategic, financial, legal, and other issues surrounding the various Flower Shows.
    The subseries also includes various working files and publicity files, especially for the New York Flower Shows. The content of these various files is uneven across the years. The files include floor plans for some of the International Flower Shows of the 1960s, held at the New York Coliseum building; a 1969 memo from Horticultural Society of New York Executive Director Alexander Allport titled "The Future of the International Flower Show," which expressed concerns that would eventually lead to the termination of those shows; publicity packets for the New York shows; sponsor lists; logistical notes; and other items.
    - International Flower Show Committee Minutes (6 folders), 1915-1942; 205707 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 6-11)
    - International Flower Show, Inc. Certificate of Incorporation, By-laws (amended to 1954), 501(c)(5) Tax Exemption (2 folders), 1942, 1958; 205708 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 12-13)
      Includes an original endorsed copy of the 1942 certificate of incorporation.
    - International Flower Show, Inc. Minutes (5 folders), 1942-1951; 205709 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 14-18)
    - International Flower Show, Inc. Minutes (12 folders), 1951-1965; 205710 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 1-12)
    - International Flower Show, Inc. Minutes (5 folders), 1965-1970; 205711 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 1-5)
    - International Flower Show, Inc. Legal, Tax, & Corporate Matters (5 folders), 1942-1969; 205712 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 6-10)
    - "The Future of the International Flower Show" Memo from Executive Director Alexander Allport, 1969 May; 205713 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 11)
    - International Flower Show History File, 1990s-2000s; 205714 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 12)
    - Preliminary International Flower Show Schedule, 1916; 205715 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 13)
    - International Flower Show Floor Plans (Folder 1 of 2), 1960s; 205716 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 14)
    - International Flower Show Floor Plans (Folder 2 of 2). Oversize, 1960s; 205717 (Drawer Oversize-Large)